Guide to the Arthur Russell Moore Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Arthur Russell Moore papers
1905-1961
SC0188
Moore, Arthur Russell, 1882-
2.75 Linear feet
Personal correspondence (1931-1961), class and laboratory notebooks (1905 -1960), typed manuscripts, and rough drafts of articles. Subjects include sea urchins, marine invertebrates, trypsin, and genetics. Correspondents include Gabrielle Donnay, Leona Metzger, John H. Northrup, Sven Horstadius, Ethel Browne Harvey, Emery F. Swan, and Richard B. Lyons. Collection also includes one notebook of his wife Mary Mitchell Moore, from Woods Hole, 1917-21.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Arthur Russell Moore received his Ph. D. in physiology from the University of California in 1911. He was a professor of physiology at the University of Oregon, 1926-48, and at the University of Portland, 1948-54. During the years 1926 to 1954 he was also a professor of biology at Stanford, lecturing during the summer at the Hopkins Marine State in Pacific Grove, California.
Description of the Collection
Personal correspondence (1931-1961), class and laboratory notebooks (1905 -1960), typed manuscripts, and rough drafts of articles. Subjects include sea urchins, marine invertebrates, trypsin, and genetics. Correspondents include Gabrielle Donnay, Leona Metzger, John H. Northrup, Sven Horstadius, Ethel Browne Harvey, Emery F. Swan, and Richard B. Lyons. Collection also includes one notebook of his wife Mary Mitchell Moore, from Woods Hole, 1917-21.
Access Terms
Donnay, Gabrielle.; Harvey, Ethel Browne, 1885; Hopkins Marine Station--Faculty.; Horstadius, Sven, 1898-; Lyons, Richard B.; Metzger, Leona.; Moore, Arthur Russell, 1882-; Moore, Mary Mitchell.; Northrup, John H.; Stanford University. Department of Zoology. Faculty.; Swan, Emery F.; Genetics.; Marine invertebrates.; Sea urchins.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Notebook, ca. 1905-09 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Experiment Notebook, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Observation Notebook, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Experimental physiology and immunology, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Marine Experiments, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Physics 11a, 1909-1915 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Research Notebook, 1911-2 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Notebook, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Research Notebook, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Research Notebook, 1917-21 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Naples: Stazione Zoologica, 1925-26 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Lab notebook, HMS, 1933-35 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - HMS Summer, 1937-38 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Notebook, 1939-41 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Notebook (1939-41), Loose Items (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Notebook 1942-43 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Hermaphrodite Dendras, 1943-48 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Nervous System, 1943-48 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Plasmodium, Eggs, and Allocentrotus 1943-61 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Notebook 1947-1955 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Notebook 1948-49 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - P.M.L. Dillon Beach 1952 [labeled 1952 but entries are 1956-60] (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Trypsin Expts.[and] Enchinocytase 1956-61 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Notebook 1958 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Greek Vase, notes on, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Mary Mitchell Moore, notebook from Woods Hole, 1917-1921 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Mary Mitchell Moore, loose items from notebook (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Notebook, 1923 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Notes on specimens gathered June-July 1946 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Notes on the Arbacia egg (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Trypsin notes (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Anaesthesia – typescript paper (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Associative Hysteresis in Larval Amblystoma – typescript paper, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Biparental Inheritance in an Interordinal Cross of Sea Urchin and San Dollar – typescript paper (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Cellular Permeability and its Basis – typescript paper (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Chemical Mediation of the Nerve Impulse – typescript paper (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Communities and Mutual Self Help Among Lower Organisms – typescript paper (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - The Cultural Value of Science, faculty lecture February 1940 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Excitation – typescript paper (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - The Extracellular Systems of the Developing Egg and their Relation to Gastrulation – typescript paper (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Formative Alterations in Sea Urchin Embryos by Means of Trypsin – typescript paper and lab notes (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Galvanotropism – typescript paper (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Hermaphrodite paper – research notes and bibliography (no finished paper) (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - The Inheritance of Skeletal Characters in an Inter-ordinal Cross of Two Echinoids – typescript paper (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - The Inheritance of Skeletal Characters of the Plutei in an Inter-ordinal Cross of Two Echinoids – typescript paper (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - The Inheritance of Skeletal Characters in the Plutei of an Inter-ordinal Cross, Strongylocentrotus [female] x Dendraster [male] – typescript paper (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Injury, Recovery and Function in an Aganglionic Central Nervous System – typescript paper, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - The Interordinal cross between Dendraster excentricus and allocentrotus fragilis – manuscript paper (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Mecanismos Fundametalis da Excitacao Nervosa – typescript paper (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - The Mechanism of Memory in the Invertebrates – typescript paper (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Methods for the Laboratory Culture of the Larvae of the Sea Urchin – typescript paper (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - On the Nature of the Hatching Enzyme of the Sea Urchin – paper and correspondence with co-author Raymond F. Jones, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Paper on acetylcholine in French – typescript paper (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Role of Salt Ions in Maintaining the Irritability of the Tissues – typescript paper (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Some Structural Characteristics of Living Substance – typescript paper (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Miscellaneous figures and illustrations (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - The Locus of the Action of the Galvanic Current in the Earthworm, Lumbricus Terrestris – typescript paper, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Modification of Embryonic Development in Echinoderms by Trypsin – typescript paper in English, manuscript in French (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - On the Locus and Nature of the Forces Causing Gastrulation in the Embryos of Dendraster Excentricus – typescript paper, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - On the Segregation of "Cleavage-Substance" in the Unfertilized Egg of Dendraster – typescript paper (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Observations on Glowworms and Observation of Color Vision in Salamander Larvae – 2 typescript papers (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Paper (incomplete) on Hermaphroditism in Echinoids (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Paper on Leonardo da Vinci – typescript (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Paper on plasmodia – typescript (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - The Problem of Inheritance in the Plutei of Echinoids – manuscript paper (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - The Process of Gastrulation in Trypsin Embryos of Dendraster Excentricus – typescript paper (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Reasons for Choosing a Career in Science – typescript paper (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - The Relation of Ions to the Appearance and Persistence of the Fertilization and Hyaline Membranes in the Eggs of the Sea Urchin – typescript paper (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Science and the Totalitarian Society – typescript paper (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Trypsin as a Parthenogenetic Agent – typescript paper (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Trypsin – page 8 of unidentified paper (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Utilization of Marine Invertebrates for Embryological Study at Pacific Grove, California (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Report on research, Jan. 9, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Bibliography (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Symposium: The Lower Metazoa, Sept. 1960 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Donnay, Gabrielle – notes and correspondence re her paper on biocrystallography, 1955-56 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Metzger, Leona – correspondence and paper 1954 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence received, 1931-49 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1951-Jan. 3, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, Jan. 14, 1957-1961 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous materials (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Frings, Hubert and Mable – several papers, 1958-60 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Hayakawa, S. I., On Communication with the Soviet Union, commencement address, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Latham, Arthur B., Rheotropism as a True Response to Current (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Motomura, Isao – bibliography, ca. 1954 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Orendurff, James and Warren R. Fleming, An Adaptive Mechanism in the Slime Mold (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Sexton, Harold, On the Antagonistic Action of Strychnine and Na- and K- Thiocyanates on Paramecia (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Papers by assorted other authors (on scientific themes) (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Russian reprint (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Original binder for lab notebook, HMS, 1933-35 (notebook pages in box 2, folder 3) (Box 6)